<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pyleoclim</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/</link><atom:link href="https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Pyleoclim</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/icon_hu5486d42984c30aaff6be99d37062b147_3155_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Pyleoclim</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/</link></image><item><title>People</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Approach</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/approach/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/approach/</guid><description>&lt;p>This page contains key sections of the &lt;strong>Final Report&lt;/strong> for the project focused on the data science methodology used to approach the problem. It should be no more than 3 pages long. It should be done after or in combination with the Requirements document. It should have an initial release after no more than eight weeks into the project, and can serve as an interim project report. It can be refined as the project progresses and the problem is better understood.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-quality">Data Quality&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Describe any steps that were used to address any issues concerning the quality of the data. This may include collecting data quality metrics, discarding subsets of the data, or applying specific techniques for handling missing values, dealing with outliers, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-preprocessing">Data Preprocessing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Describe the steps taken to preprocess the raw data to prepare it for analysis. This may include data transformations to convert to a required format, feature engineering operations, encoding features as binary, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="exploratory-data-analysis-eda">Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA)&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Discuss any techniques employed to gain insights into the data. This could include data visualizations, generating summary statistics, initial analysis, and other exploratory techniques used to understand the data distributions, features, and helpful patterns.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="model-development">Model Development&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Describe the algorithms, methodology, and architectures used to generate models. Discuss how models were generated, seeded, and improved. Show the libraries and frameworks used for model development, as well as the rationale behind those choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="model-evaluation">Model Evaluation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Discuss the evaluation metrics used to assess model performance, and justify those choices based on the problem that the project is addressing. Describe the evaluation techniques used, such as cross-validation, and how undesirable model behaviors, such as overfitting, were avoided.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data Assessment</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/data/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/data/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This page serves as a Data Assessment Document for the project. It should be no more than 2-3 pages long. It can be drafted in the first two weeks of the project, and can serve as an interim project report. It can be refined as the project progresses and the use of the data is better understood.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-overview-and-examples">Data Overview and Examples&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Give a brief description of the data provided for this project, what it represents, how it was collected, and why it may help address the problem you are tackling. Discuss if you will be using all the data or only some subset of it for the project. Consider possible additional data that may be publicly available in the open Web that might complement the data that you are given.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-accessibility">Data Accessibility&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Summarize how the data can be accessed. For example, data may be available for download in files, or accessible through an API, or can be queried from a database. Mention any restrictions in accessing the data, for example if it is sensitive data that can only accessed with special permission.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-formats">Data Formats&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Describe briefly the formats of the data. Common data formats include CSV, JSON, XML, shapefiles, or any other specific formats relevant to your website.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-challenges">Data Challenges&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Summarize why analyzing this data will be challenging. This may include issues like data heterogeneity, data size, and any pre- or post-processing needs. Explain some ideas for how these challenges could be addressed.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="data-visualizations-and-highlights">Data Visualizations and Highlights&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Including a visualization is a simple way to show something interesting about the data. Perhaps the visualizations could simply highlight the size, distribution, and other simple statistical characteristics of the data.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Problem and Requirements</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/problem-statement/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/problem-statement/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="target-for-the-semester">Target for the Semester&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Outlier detection:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>KNN: This issue aims to explore how KNN works for timeseries data especially on paleoclimate data. Moreover, we also implement automate auto-tuning of the parameters using the silhouette method to heuristically determine all parameters&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Visualization
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SciencePlots: API for developing standardized plot styles using MatPlotLib (plots for IEEE, science, nature articles)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>BoxPlots: This issue contends with the use pandas and Plotly to represent change in paleoclimatic data over the course of decades through the use of box plots to measure change in Southern Oscillation Index value&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fluctuation Analysis
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>HAAR: Current Pyleoclim Time Series analysis are effective yet costly due to our data’s characteristics. Haar Analysis improves the efficiency, forecasting quality, and particularly useful for data compression and denoising applications. Implement a working Haar Fluctuation Analysis Method for our data based on previous research algorithms created for similar data.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="approach">Approach&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Outlier detection&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>KNN on anomaly detection:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For KNN on anomaly detection, it involves identifying data points that deviate significantly from the majority of the data&lt;/li>
&lt;li>KNN: Leveraging sklearn LocalOutlierFactor() function&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Silhouette method: A metric used to assess the quality of clustering, we’re using it to evaluate the performance of models&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Visualization&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>SciencePlots Functionality:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Generate notebook with Pyleoclim/SciencePlot plot comparisons (IP)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Add SciencePlots into Pyelo dependencies and environment (IP)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Append new SciencePlot styles to Pyleo Plot.py file&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Create Unit Test to ensure smooth integration of Scienceplots&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Develop Scienceplots PyleoTutorial&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Box plots for Time Series Data
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Use .astype function of pandas to group points from the same year into one dataset&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Generate boxplot using Plotly to juxtapose each year’s data and measure annual changes in the Southern Oscillation Index value&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Fluctuation Analysis&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Haar Fluctuation Analysis:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Determine notation and good defaults values for our method&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Incorporate haar_v2 in Pyleoclim as a method of the Series class&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Use this method to reproduce a findings similar to past research on some of Pyleoclim’s pre-defined timeseries&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Figure out a good unit test for this method&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Implement it&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="use-case-scenario">Use Case Scenario&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>KNN on anomaly detection
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="KNN" srcset="
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/KNN_hu2a94a172e575f39ce12d33e749069ccd_865902_f67c2a637ebcf85c6a8c5407563585ee.webp 400w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/KNN_hu2a94a172e575f39ce12d33e749069ccd_865902_ed34850942459afbf83fa119ba7ba1ec.webp 760w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/KNN_hu2a94a172e575f39ce12d33e749069ccd_865902_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/KNN_hu2a94a172e575f39ce12d33e749069ccd_865902_f67c2a637ebcf85c6a8c5407563585ee.webp"
width="760"
height="453"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>SciencePlots Functionality
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SciencePlot" srcset="
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/SciencePlot_hue53c0585a3656a7802f55921389acd46_558748_70bc530524defbfd9db5e5fdacb88de8.webp 400w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/SciencePlot_hue53c0585a3656a7802f55921389acd46_558748_37519a784d7e7e6d18c5f3d962ea48c4.webp 760w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/SciencePlot_hue53c0585a3656a7802f55921389acd46_558748_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/SciencePlot_hue53c0585a3656a7802f55921389acd46_558748_70bc530524defbfd9db5e5fdacb88de8.webp"
width="760"
height="723"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Box plots for Time Series Data
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="BoxPlot" srcset="
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/BoxPlot_hud35fdf79162f97069444f0044661fe9e_309527_7f40dc3ec8ecb8fd5fa9b359cb20ec0c.webp 400w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/BoxPlot_hud35fdf79162f97069444f0044661fe9e_309527_87d3f2493c2783fc8e2d4db500dd78fb.webp 760w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/BoxPlot_hud35fdf79162f97069444f0044661fe9e_309527_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/BoxPlot_hud35fdf79162f97069444f0044661fe9e_309527_7f40dc3ec8ecb8fd5fa9b359cb20ec0c.webp"
width="760"
height="339"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Fluctuation Analysis
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="HAAR" srcset="
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/HAAR_hue509a8f43b728e8b7604955ed9a83e23_152515_38d1e155267b6ecd77725f26d40eea45.webp 400w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/HAAR_hue509a8f43b728e8b7604955ed9a83e23_152515_249e8a6171a2267abc41deb6e687786d.webp 760w,
/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/HAAR_hue509a8f43b728e8b7604955ed9a83e23_152515_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w"
src="https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/2023-fall-paleoclimate/media/HAAR_hue509a8f43b728e8b7604955ed9a83e23_152515_38d1e155267b6ecd77725f26d40eea45.webp"
width="760"
height="547"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Results</title><link>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/results/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ckids-datafest.github.io/2023-fall-paleoclimate/results/</guid><description>&lt;p>This page contains key sections of the &lt;strong>Final Report&lt;/strong> for the project focused on results to date. It should be no more than 2 pages long. An initial draft can be created at any point during the project, and can be refined as the project progresses.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="system-and-model-performance">System and Model Performance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Show the performance of the best system and model(s) developed, showing clearly the performance metrics and improvements over the baseline system as appropriate. Create visualizations that show clearly these results.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="discussion-of-findings">Discussion of Findings&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Offer a discussion of the main findings using the system developed. Put the results in the context of the original problem statement and the questions that were posed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Discuss any unexpected results, and potential explanations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Enumerate (ideally in bullets) the most important findings, and their impact on your project goals.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="limitations-and-future-work">Limitations and Future Work&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Discuss any limitations of the work to date, how these limitations could be addressed in future work. Discuss what lines of work are most promising given the understanding of the problem and the data gained throughout the project.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>